<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "AAR_Template.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<appendix id="appe-participant-feedback">
  <title>Participant Feedback</title>
  <section>
    <title>General Participant Feedback</title>
    <para>
      A large number of comments were received from participants over
      various circuits.  The following is a sampling of those comments.
      Note that in some cases, sut/paste preserved grammatical, spelling
      and typographic errors, in other cases they were introduced in
      transcription.
    </para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist >
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Utilizing the UP Traffic Net worked very well.  There were a
	    number of check-ins, messages were passed by the EC's that
	    were involved this year through the UP Net
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Aileen WA8DHB, Net control of the UP Net did an excellent job,
	    including having downstate stations sending some of our
	    traffic to the SEOC.  I don't know if she received any
	    information about the SET besides our conversations on the
	    phone.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Deployed one Emergency Response Veichle, Manned the Chapter
	    radio room using HF,Packet in Converse mode,CW, Red Cross Low
	    Band FM and 2mtr simplex. Had laison on E Team and the MVHF
	    Traffic net. Took and sent NTS traffic,passed tactical traffic
	    in converse mode Contacts made with Allegan Red Cross.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Be careful of abbreviations in NTS messages 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    some might not know what they mean Using State wide repeater
	    system depended too much on infrastructure to link Counties
	    together
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Some OP'S not familiar with NTS slowed the net down with fills
	    and some inattentiveness
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    SET info not found on State ARRL web site or on Yahoo Groups-
	    Many didn't know the State was doing one
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Lack of a designated 60 mtr freq to fall back on/alternate
	    freq's determined in advance by NM's So what if some hams
	    don't have 60?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    NM's need to think out side the box- That is spread the net
	    out on alternate freq's with NCS reporting back to the main
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    NCS need increased circuits to pass traffic
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Some DEC's did nothing in their counties causing failure in
	    these counties
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Suggest organizing the HF nets more like Skywarn nets are run
	    - a main net and several sub nets This will allow disaster
	    traffic to be moved more quickly
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    RED CROSS: Radio room needs to be reorganized- More space for
	    operating and sound deadening dividers and headphones Upgrade
	    of laptops and printers more NTS training common pwr
	    connectors Check deployment boxes more often- Even though
	    packet went well more trng needed.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    What Went Well:On site equipment helped rapid deployment
	    Packet in converse mode Had more then enough comm circuits to
	    pass traffic Knowledgeable operators on Packet solved minor
	    problems with TNC's MVHF Traffic Net operators very
	    knowledgeable and performed very well HF Liaisons great- Basic
	    concept of the exercise developed by the State on the right
	    track- Could use as many exercises as the State can arrange!
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    no man-made interference
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Representation from SEOC, Districts 1,5,6 and 7
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Excellent scores compared to SET of October 2009
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Net liaisons extremely competent in obtaining traffic from HF
	    and returning with outgoing traffic
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Very good communications between VHF and SEOC
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Goodly number of stations on emergency power
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Extremely efficient assistance from E-Team in Kent county and
	    also participation from Kent County Red Cross and one other
	    Red Cross facility in a different District
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Messages from SEOC began coming through in a timely manner and
	    there was no wasted air space like in previous years
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Brief periods of time were allotted at the top of each hour
	    for stations not involved in the exercise so that they may
	    transmit any priority or welfare traffic
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    As a net control I need to learn to obtain my rogers and
	    provide fills for the exercise participants in a more
	    efficient manner
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    My net liaisons need to learn to give traffic more slowly thus
	    leading to a possibility of less fills being required
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    It was apparent that several stations needed NTS training as
	    excess time was used in getting their traffic passed
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Need more stations on emergency power
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    I had difficulty communicating with three stations most likely
	    due to their equipment as the links they were using were in
	    good operating order
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    One station left early after being asked to take traffic and i
	    got the impression that because of their lack of skill they
	    felt unable to continue but perhaps i could be in error.
	    while on the air the station was very efficient and seemed to
	    know the proper protocol
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The Liaison who was monitoring the SEOC phone Net picked up
	    three messages and brought them to the MIDTN, messages # 2, 4,
	    9 and where picked up and acknowledged by all four Counties in
	    the NET. A repeat was not needed as they where monitoring the
	    NET.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Mike in Presque Isle picked up a VHF message # 41 to the
	    effect that all power State wide was lost and if you where
	    without backup you were done until the exercise ended
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    MIDTN as well as Roscommon, Alpena and Presque Isle all had
	    Emergency Power Sources and switched over and rechecked into
	    the NET to acknowledge same
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    We operated from the Roscommon Fairgrounds as a field day type
	    station and erected antennas and used equipment we brought to
	    the scene. I worked elbow to elbow with the DEC (Red) and he
	    spent a great deal of time after the exercise teaching me what
	    I needed to do to function better as a Manager of the NET
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    I checked into QMN because the statewide SSB nets were very
	    weak into this location.  Also, they were yakking away for
	    minutes at a time, explaining why things were like they were
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Major concern on these nets were on frequencies other than
	    their usual frequencies.  Also, I believe some folks on the
	    3553 KHz freq for QMN were likewise concerned.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Repeater contacts went well with all stations hearing
	    everyone. Analog simplex contacts were generally acceptable,
	    but we found that some electrical noise at the Coldwater PD/FD
	    was not allowing them to hear weak signals. D-Star simplex
	    contacts had the same result as analog simplex as a result of
	    the high noise levels at CPD. Steuben has no D-Star capability
	    at this time. The high noise levels have been resolved at CPD
	    by utilizing adding grounding to the shield of our antenna
	    run.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Both the Hillsdale and Branch EOCs had extreme electronic
	    noise and no packet connections were possible. We are using
	    toroids and grounding devices to try to quiet things down but
	    we are not there yet.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    We had 17 participants with 16 on emergency power.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The contact with Kalamazoo on the 04 repeater was successful
	    from the EOC. The Coldwater hospital had difficulty. Virtually
	    everything on simplex and D-Star failed. We question band
	    conditions because this has not been particularly problematic
	    in the past. Will test again in November.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Checking into the MACS Net went well. We received 4 pieces of
	    traffic and we sent 1 response to the SEOC. Over all, my
	    impression was that the HF link to limited stations who
	    communicated with the SEOC worked very well. This moved the
	    gridlock away from the SEOC. I did not have the chance to
	    listen to anything but the MACS Net, so things may have gone
	    to hell in a hand basket elsewhere. At least there were
	    trained traffic handlers at the SEOC and at the helm of the HF
	    Nets. This exercise illustrates that ARES and RACES groups
	    need a ton of work on how to properly and accurately formulate
	    and relay written messages to another operator. This is Deja
	    vu all over again!!!!
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Our monthly Tornado Siren Test went off well, after the power
	    cable of the signaling equipment at the 911 Center was plugged
	    back in. It turns out that some things at 911 had been
	    rearranged and they neglected to plug the unit back in. Good
	    thing they test things!!!!
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Moving frequencies off usual freqs created considerable
	    confusion.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    I was a W8DC, and was assigned to monitor 3932 KHz, but
	    signals were so weak I could hardly hear anyone.  So, I moved
	    here to 3553 KHz for QMN, even though QMN was supposed to be
	    for District 1 only (at least that was my impression.)  Best
	    laid plans of mice and men often go astray in emergency.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Moving to 7 MHz was a fine idea, but I wasn't sure everyone
	    heard the QNC to move, so I voluteered to run a parallel
	    session on 3.5 MHz.  I found W8OAK, quite weak, but he was
	    able to hear enough to move to 7068 KHz and, apparently moved
	    his traffic.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The SEOC had a good signal during the two hours I operated.
	    Conditions were fair to good.  No problems here.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    It's refreshing to know that we have sufficient depth of
	    operators with CW skills so that a CW operator at the SEOC is
	    available for the exercise.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The segregated net concept, that is, a watch frequency for the
	    SEOC and a separate net frequency for QMN was problematic.
	    While this may have worked well for the voice nets, which tend
	    to have a larger contingent of operators, it tended to divide
	    the limited resources of QMN.  Rather than resulting in
	    greater efficiency, it resulted in a cumbersome flow of
	    traffic and duplication of resources.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Operations during the 8:00-AM to 8:20-AM EDT time frame on
	    3563 was hampered by strong digital interference.  I did not
	    have the capabilities to decode the traffic.  However, it was
	    quite strong at my location.  It seems to me the risk of such
	    frequency conflicts is greater when nets are moved off their
	    normal frequencies or when special nets are established
	    without thought given to frequency coordination and potential
	    conflicts.  For example, when the QMN frequencies were
	    selected (both primary and alternate), considerable time and
	    monitoring was invested to make sure the conflict with other
	    nets throughout the day would be minimized.  Of course, there
	    are no guarantees, but it seems to me such interference could
	    have been problematic in a real communications emergency.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The procedures and message traffic originated and relayed was
	    quite good. All operators involved did a fine job.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Message 001: The x-ray at the conclusion of the text and
	    before the second break (to signature) was unnecessary.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    In time of emergency, and therefore in drills and exercises,
	    the message should have included a time of origination.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Message 007: No time of origin.  This is a potential problem
	    in an Emergency Operations Center when multiple messages may
	    be received about a single event.  In order for an agency or
	    individual to construct a coherent understanding of an event,
	    it is necessary to know the sequence of the event components,
	    inquiries, and actions that take place.  Otherwise, errors in
	    judgment occur.  The time of origin should reflect the time at
	    which the message was drafted by the signatory.  As such,
	    automatic time stamp at time of entry into a network is
	    inaccurate and inappropriate (e.g. packet time stamp, e-mail
	    time stamp, etc.).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Message 007: Who is requesting the information?  If I were to
	    contact my local DPW or Road Commission and make this inquiry,
	    someone is bound to ask "on whose authority are you making
	    this request and who wants the information?"  It is also
	    likely to generate a reply; to whom is that reply addressed?
	    When a message is originated on behalf of the SEOC, it should
	    have an authorizing signature.  Obviously, no harm no foul as
	    this was a drill message, but in real life, it should include
	    a name, title and agency in the signature line.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    I attempted to access the W8HVG link system, but the
	    St. Joseph repeater was locked key-down all day.  Not sure if
	    this was an interference problem or malicious.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Thank you to K8KIC for checking in on behalf of District One!
	    A life-saver.  We need more members in District One.
	  </para>
	</listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>General Comments from Evaluators</title>
    <para>
      Most evaluator comments are included in <xref
      linkend="sect-analysis" />.  However, evaluators were also given the
      opportunity to provide general observations.  Those observations
      are listed below.
    </para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    All major players need three HF rigs and 3 VHF
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    One HF rig at DEC went down and was out of use two
	    hours in a real emergency I would have brought in my
	    HF mobile
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Alt NCS training heeded. DEC 7 pri op saw no need for
	    alt NCS/Alt freq until instructed by DEC to open one
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    I think master list of participant rigs would be
	    useful. Until drill I never knew RLI and I use same
	    rigs
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Interoperability priority needed
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Communications involving SET - with other nets that
	    usually meet during this time period woule solve a lot
	    of time and net problems - reference the Old Geisers
	    net - Communications with them ahead of time about the
	    SET so they could QSY the net ahead of time
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Traffic being repeated at too fast a pace verbally -
	    repeated msg incorrect - District not getting the
	    State traffic in a timely fashion - reliability and
	    accuracy
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Operators need more practice copying messages -
	    station on freq not prepared to copy - xray in message
	    not being put into word count causing confusion
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Some stations monitoring both VHF and HF copying their
	    traffic ahead of time to insure accuracy
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Confusion about abbreviations in text of message and
	    not what to do about it. Ref Msg No. 46 - E Power
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    I couldn't stand by idly; I ended up making
	    transmissions to help patch and relay traffic. I ended
	    up somewhat of a coordinator.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<!--            <listitem>
	     <para>
	     KB8RCR on HF has an alligator station - all strong
	     signal but no ears
	     </para>
	     </listitem> -->
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    I was on 3952. I spoke to NKX and K8YYZ
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    60 meters needs to be tested.  Thinking knee-jerk to
	    run to 40 meters is not the only alternative to 75
	    meters.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    It became obvious that the 5th District has a big
	    administrative communications problem.  It wasn't for
	    lack of trying to get the SET word out.  The problem
	    was that 2 of 4 counties, Allegan and Calhoun, kept
	    their operations a secret.  Allegan Co. Operated in a
	    vacuum but had a busy county-only exercise. There ids
	    a 5th district yahoo egroup the works well if people
	    use it."
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    As Kalamazoo County EC, NK8X read all of the traffic
	    from the SEOC on the local VHF-FM net frequency.  NK8X
	    also assisted the NCS on 3952 as a relay.  75 meters
	    pooped out around 10:30AM."
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>

<!--
  <note><para>This section is optional</para></note>
  <para>
    [Provided in this section is a sample Participant Feedback Form, which
    should be distributed to exercise participants at a post-exercise hot wash.
    Appendix C of the AAR/IP should provide a summary of the feedback received
    through this form.]
  </para>
  <formalpara>
    <title>Participant Feedback Form</title>
    <para>
      Exercise name: &nbsp; &EXNAM; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 
      Exercise Date: &nbsp; &EXDATE;
    </para>
  </formalpara>
  <para>
    Agency: ________________________________________
  </para>
  <para>
    Role: ___Player ___Observer ___Facilitator ___Evaluator
  </para>
  <formalpara>
    <title>Recommendations and Corrective Actions</title>
    <para>&nbsp;</para>
  </formalpara>
  <para>
    1. Based on the exercise today and the tasks identified, list the top 3
    strengths and/or areas that need improvement:
  </para>
  <para>
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
  </para>
  <para>
    2. 1.Is there anything you saw in the exercise that the evaluator(s) might
    not have been able to experience, observe, and record?
  </para>
  <para>
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
  </para>
  <para>
    3. Identify the corrective actions that should be taken to address the
    issues identified above.  For each corrective action, indicate if it is a
    high, medium, or low priority.
  </para>
  <para>
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
  </para>
  <para>
    4. 1.Describe the corrective actions that relate to your area of
    responsibility.  Who should be assigned responsibility for each corrective
    action?
  </para>
  <para>
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
  </para>
  <para>
    5. 1.List the applicable equipment, training, policies, plans, and
    procedures that should be reviewed, revised, or developed.  Indicate the
    priority level for each.
  </para>
  <para>
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
  </para>
  <formalpara>
    <title>Exercise Design and Conduct: Assessment</title>
    <para>
      Please rate, on a scale of 1 to 5, your overall assessment of the exercise
      relative to the statements provided below, with 1 indicating strong
      disagreement with the statement and 5 indicating strong agreement.
    </para>
  </formalpara>
  <table frame="all">
    <title>Participant Assessment</title>
    <tgroup cols="6">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="5*" />
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*" />
      <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="1*" />
      <colspec colnum="4" colname="c4" colwidth="1*" />
      <colspec colnum="5" colname="c5" colwidth="1*" />
      <colspec colnum="6" colname="c6" colwidth="1*" />
      <thead>
	<row>
	  <entry valign="middle">Assessment Factor</entry>
	  <entry colsep="0">Strongly Disagree</entry>
	  <entry colsep="0"></entry>
	  <entry colsep="0"></entry>
	  <entry colsep="0"></entry>
	  <entry>Strongly Agree</entry>
	</row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
	<row>
	  <entry>The exercise was well structured and organized.</entry>
	  <entry align="center">1</entry>
	  <entry align="center">2</entry>
	  <entry align="center">3</entry>
	  <entry align="center">4</entry>
	  <entry align="center">5</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>The exercise scenario was plausible and realistic.</entry>
	  <entry align="center">1</entry>
	  <entry align="center">2</entry>
	  <entry align="center">3</entry>
	  <entry align="center">4</entry>
	  <entry align="center">5</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>The facilitator/controller(s) was knowledgeable about the area of play and kept the exercise on target.</entry>
	  <entry align="center">1</entry>
	  <entry align="center">2</entry>
	  <entry align="center">3</entry>
	  <entry align="center">4</entry>
	  <entry align="center">5</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>The exercise documentation provided to assist in preparing for and participating in the exercise was useful.</entry>
	  <entry align="center">1</entry>
	  <entry align="center">2</entry>
	  <entry align="center">3</entry>
	  <entry align="center">4</entry>
	  <entry align="center">5</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>Participation in the exercise was appropriate for someone in my position.</entry>
	  <entry align="center">1</entry>
	  <entry align="center">2</entry>
	  <entry align="center">3</entry>
	  <entry align="center">4</entry>
	  <entry align="center">5</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>The participants included the right people in terms of level and mix of disciplines.</entry>
	  <entry align="center">1</entry>
	  <entry align="center">2</entry>
	  <entry align="center">3</entry>
	  <entry align="center">4</entry>
	  <entry align="center">5</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>This exercise allowed my agency/jurisdiction to practice and improve priority capabilities.</entry>
	  <entry align="center">1</entry>
	  <entry align="center">2</entry>
	  <entry align="center">3</entry>
	  <entry align="center">4</entry>
	  <entry align="center">5</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>After this exercise, I believe my agency/jurisdiction is better prepared to deal successfully with the scenario that was exercised.</entry>
	  <entry align="center">1</entry>
	  <entry align="center">2</entry>
	  <entry align="center">3</entry>
	  <entry align="center">4</entry>
	  <entry align="center">5</entry>
	</row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>

  <formalpara>
    <title>Participant Feedback</title>
    <para>
      Please provide any recommendations on how this exercise or future exercises could be improved or enhanced. 
    </para>
  </formalpara>
  <para>
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
    ____________________________________________________________________
  </para>
-->
</appendix>
