<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "SET2011-After_Action_Report.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="sect-exer-overview" lang="en-US">
	<title>Executive Overview</title>
	 <indexterm>
		<primary>ARES</primary>
		 <secondary>Relationship with NTS</secondary>

	</indexterm>
	 <indexterm>
		<primary>NTS</primary>
		 <secondary>Relationship with ARES</secondary>

	</indexterm>
	 <indexterm>
		<primary>ARRL Simulated Emergency Test</primary>

	</indexterm>
	 <indexterm>
		<primary>Simulated Emergency Test</primary>

	</indexterm>
	 <para>
		This exercise aimed to strengthen the relationship between the Amateur Radio Emergency Services (ARES) and the National Traffic System (NTS). The station at the State Emergency Operations Center (SEOC) delivered injects to liaisons to the various NTS nets who, in turn, delivered those injects to the Districts.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Each District was assigned an NTS net, with the expectation that this assignment would be more or less permanent. ARES District Emergency Coordinators were encouraged to work together with NTS Net Managers to plan meeting times, frequencies, etc. The Great Lakes Emergency and traffic Net was assigned the responsibility of representing the four National Weather Service offices in Michigan.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Evaluators monitored the activity looking for evidence of planning, ability to maintain communications across the state, and ability to respond to loss of infrastructure.
	</para>
	 <para>
		As this exercise was conducted in conjunction with the annual ARRL Simulated Emergency Test, individual jurisdictions were encouraged to include local government agencies and NGOs in their local activities.
	</para>
	 <section>
		<title>Exercise Details</title>
		 <para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<filename>Exercise Name</filename> - 2011 ARRL Simulated Emergency Test
					</para>

				</listitem>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						<filename>Type of exercise </filename> - The Section-wide portion of the exercise was a functional drill, testing limited capabilities within the section. However, many jurisdictions, in keeping with the spirit of the ARRL test, engaged numerous other agencies on a local level.
					</para>

				</listitem>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						<filename>Exercise Date and Duration</filename> - October 1, 2011 - 4 hours
					</para>

				</listitem>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						<filename>Location</filename> - Statewide
					</para>

				</listitem>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						<filename>Sponsor</filename> - Michigan Section of The American Radio Relay League
					</para>

				</listitem>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						<filename>Program</filename> - n/a
					</para>

				</listitem>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						<filename>Mission</filename> - Respond
					</para>

				</listitem>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						<filename>Scenario Type</filename> - Winter Storm
					</para>

				</listitem>

			</itemizedlist>

		</para>
		 <!-- 
      <section>
	<title>Exercise Name</title>
	<para>
	  2011 ARRL Simulated Emergency Test
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Type of exercise</title>
	<para>
	  The Section-wide portion of the exercise was a functional
	  drill, testing limited capabilities within the section.
	  However, several jurisdictions, in keeping with the spirit
	  of the ARRL test, engaqged numerous other agencies on a
	  local level.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Exercise start date</title>
	<para>
	  October 1, 2011
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Exercise end date</title>
	<para>
	  October 1, 2011
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Duration</title>
	<para>
	  4 Hours
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Location</title>
	<para>
	  Statewide
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Sponsor</title>
	<para>
	  Michigan Section of The American Radio Relay League
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Program</title>
	<para>
	  n/a
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Mission</title>
	<para>
	  Respond
	</para>
      </section>
 --> <section>
			<title>Capabilities</title>
			 <indexterm>
				<primary>ComA2.4.3.1</primary>

			</indexterm>
			 <indexterm>
				<primary>ComC1.2.2</primary>

			</indexterm>
			 <indexterm>
				<primary>Continuity of Operations Plans</primary>

			</indexterm>
			 <indexterm>
				<primary>Plans</primary>
				 <secondary>Continuity of Operations</secondary>

			</indexterm>
			 <indexterm>
				<primary>COOP</primary>

			</indexterm>
			 <indexterm>
				<primary>Sustained Response</primary>

			</indexterm>
			 <indexterm>
				<primary>Response</primary>
				 <secondary>Sustained</secondary>

			</indexterm>
			 <para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							ComA2.4.3.1 - Develop Standard Operating Procedures and Standard Operating Guides in support of Emergency Operations Plans. 
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										Continuity of Operation (COOP) plans describe how personnel, equipment, and other resources support sustained response/survivability and recovery for all sectors
									</para>

								</listitem>
								 <listitem>
									<para>
										Emergency response plans address substantial loss of public safety response capabilities during catastrophic events (to include special needs populations and people with disabilities)
									</para>

								</listitem>

							</itemizedlist>

						</para>

					</listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
							ComC1.2.2 - Develop common communication and data standards to facilitate the exchange of information in support of response management 
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										Develop common communication and data standards to facilitate the exchange of information in support of response management
									</para>

								</listitem>
								 <listitem>
									<para>
										Redundant and diverse interoperable communication systems are available
									</para>

								</listitem>

							</itemizedlist>

						</para>

					</listitem>

				</itemizedlist>

			</para>

		</section>
		
		 <!--       <section>
	<title>Scenario type</title>
	<para>
	  Winter storm
	</para>
      </section>  -->
	</section>
	
	 <section>
		<title>Exercise Planning team</title>
		 <para>
			The Section Emergency Coordinator (who also serves as the Section Traffic Manager) and the Section's Training and Exercise Officer planned the exercise. District Emergency Coordinators and Net Managers provided input on who was intending to participate, their capabilities, etc.
		</para>

	</section>
	
	 <section>
		<title>Participating organizations</title>
		 <para>
			The Statewide portion of the exercise included the National Traffic System nets and the Amateur Radio Emergency Services. Because their capabilities did not map any of the needs for the exercise, the Thumb and Mid-Michigan Traffic Net was not asked to participate. Several individual counties also chose not to participate.
		</para>
		 <para>
			The National Weather Service office at White Lake provided the initial injects, as well as simulations based on historical events to add realism to the scenario.
		</para>
		 <para>
			At the local level, counties were encouraged to include served agencies. In various jurisdictions, participants included the American Red Cross, Salvation Army, local Health Departments, hospitals, and a large number of Townships.
		</para>
		 <para>
			Most counties used the station at their county Emergency Operations Center as the main point of contact. Several jurisdictions also operated from hospitals, township halls and fire barns, as well as Red Cross chapters.
		</para>
		 <section>
			<title>Number of participants</title>
			 <para>
				<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Players - approx 200
						</para>

					</listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
							Controllers - 1
						</para>

					</listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
							Evaluators - 5
						</para>

					</listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
							Facilitators - none
						</para>

					</listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
							Observers - not available
						</para>

					</listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
							Victim role players - not applicable
						</para>

					</listitem>

				</itemizedlist>

			</para>

		</section>
		

	</section>

</section>


